<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" 
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
  xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd">

<channel>
      <title>Writings in consequently.org: Greg Restall’s website </title>
	  <itunes:subtitle>Greg Restall's publications on logic and philosophy</itunes:subtitle>
	  <itunes:author>Greg Restall</itunes:author>
	  <itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:name>Greg Restall</itunes:name>
	  <itunes:email>greg@consequently.org</itunes:email>
	  </itunes:owner>
	  <itunes:category text="Education">
	  <itunes:category text="Higher Education"/>
	  </itunes:category>
	  <itunes:keywords>Philosophy, Logic, mathematics, pdf, research, University, Greg Restall, Melbourne, Australia, Victoria</itunes:keywords>
	  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
	  <itunes:image href="http://consequently.org/img/avatar2.jpg" />
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://consequently.org/writing/index.xml</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    
    <updated>Fri, 14 Oct 2016 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>First Degree Entailment, Symmetry and Paradox</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/fde-symmetry-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/fde-symmetry-paradox/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Here is a puzzle, which I learned from Terence Parsons in his paper “True Contradictions”. First Degree Entailment (FDE) is a logic which allows for truth value gaps as well as truth value gluts. If you are agnostic between assigning paradoxical sentences gaps and gluts (and there seems to be no very good reason to prefer gaps over gluts or gluts over gaps if you are happy with FDE), then this looks no different, in effect, from assigning them a gap value? After all, on both views you end up with a theory that doesn&amp;rsquo;t commit you to the paradoxical sentence or its negation. How is the FDE theory any different from the theory with gaps alone?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I will present a clear answer to this puzzle&amp;mdash;an answer that explains how being agnostic between gaps and gluts is a genuinely different position than admitting gaps alone, by using the formal notion of a bi-theory, and showing that while such positions might agree on what is to be accepted, they differ on what is to be rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Existence and Definedness: the semantics of possibility and necessity</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/existence-definedness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/existence-definedness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I will address just some of Professor Williamson&amp;rsquo;s treatment of necessitism in his &lt;em&gt;Modal Logic as Metaphysics&lt;/em&gt;. I will give an account of what space might remain for a principled and logically disciplined contingentism. I agree with Williamson that those interested in the metaphysics of modality would do well to take quantified modal logic&amp;mdash;and its semantics&amp;mdash;seriously in order to be clear, systematic and precise concerning the commitments we undertake in adopting an account of modality and ontology. Where we differ is in how we present the semantics of that modal logic. I will illustrate how &lt;em&gt;proof theory&lt;/em&gt; may play a distinctive role in elaborating a quantified modal logic, and in the development of theories of meaning, and in the metaphysics of modality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper was first written for presentation in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.philo.ntu.edu.tw/lmmgroup/?mode=events_detail&amp;amp;n=1&#34;&gt;workshop on Tim Williamson&amp;rsquo;s work, at the Asian Workshop in Philosophical Logic and the Taiwan Philosophical Logic Colloquium&lt;/a&gt; at the National Taiwan University. The slides from that talk are &lt;a href=&#34;http://consequently.org/presentation/2016/existence-definedness-awpl-tplc&#34;&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Review of Thomas Piecha and Peter Schroeder-Heister (editors), Advances in Proof-Theoretic Semantics</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/advances-in-pts-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/advances-in-pts-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;What could you mean by the term &amp;ldquo;proof-theoretic semantics&amp;rdquo; (PTS)? At first glance, it could mean either the semantics &lt;em&gt;of&lt;/em&gt; proof theory, or perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s more likely to mean semantics conducted &lt;em&gt;using the tools of proof theory&lt;/em&gt;. And &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;s the enterprise that the fifteen authors intend to advance in the sixteen papers in this edited collection&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Fixed Point Models for Theories of Properties and Classes</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/fixed-point-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/fixed-point-models/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;There is a vibrant (but minority) community among philosophical logicians seeking to resolve the paradoxes of classes, properties and truth by way of adopting some non-classical logic in which trivialising paradoxical arguments are not valid. There is also a long tradition in theoretical computer science&amp;ndash;going back to Dana Scott’s fixed point model construction for the untyped lambda-calculus&amp;ndash;of models allowing for  fixed points. In this paper, I will bring these traditions closer together, to show how these model constructions can shed light on what we could hope for in a non-trivial model of a theory for classes, properties or truth featuring fixed points.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>On Priest on Nonmonotonic and Inductive Logic</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/on-priest-on-nonmonotonic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/on-priest-on-nonmonotonic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Graham Priest defends the use of a nonmonotonic logic, &lt;em&gt;LPm&lt;/em&gt;, in his analysis of reasoning in the face of true contradictions, such as those arising from the paradoxes of self-reference. In the course of defending the choice of this logic in the face of the criticism that &lt;em&gt;LPm&lt;/em&gt; is not truth preserving, Priest argued that requirement is too much to ask: since &lt;em&gt;LPm&lt;/em&gt; is a nonmonotonic logic, it necessarily fails to preserve truth. In this paper, I show that this assumption is incorrect, and I explain why nonmonotonic logics can nonetheless be truth preserving. Finally, I diagnose Priest&amp;rsquo;s error, to explain when nonmonotonic logics do indeed fail to preserve truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham Priest has written a &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/tht3.204&#34;&gt;very short reply&lt;/a&gt; to this article, which also appears in &lt;em&gt;Thought&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Three Cultures—or: what place for logic in the humanities?</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/three-cultures/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/three-cultures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Logic has been an important part of philosophy since the work of Aristotle in the 4th Century BCE. Developments of the 19th and the 20th Century saw an incredible flowering of mathematical techniques in logic, and the discipline transformed beyond recognition into something that can seem forbiddingly technical and formal. The discipline of logic plays a vital role in mathematics, linguistics, computer science and electrical engineering, and it may seem that it no longer has a place within the humanities.
In this essay, I show why this perception is misplaced and dangerous, and that in a time of increasing specialisation and differentiation between the cultures of the humanities, the sciences, and of engineering, logic not only has much to give to the humanities, it also has much to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Generality and Existence I: Quantification and Free Logic</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/generality-and-existence-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/generality-and-existence-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I motivate a cut free sequent calculus for classical logic with first order quantification, allowing for singular terms free of existential import. Along the way, I motivate a criterion for rules designed to answer Prior&amp;rsquo;s question about what distinguishes rules for logical concepts, like &amp;lsquo;conjunction&amp;rsquo; from apparently similar rules for putative concepts like &amp;lsquo;tonk&amp;rsquo;, and I show that the rules for the quantifiers&amp;mdash;and the existence predicate&amp;mdash;satisfy that condition.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Assertion, Denial, Accepting, Rejecting, Symmetry and Paradox</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/assertiondenialparadox/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/assertiondenialparadox/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Proponents of a dialethic or &amp;ldquo;truth-value glut&amp;rdquo; response to the paradoxes of self-reference argue that &amp;ldquo;truth-value gap&amp;rdquo; analyses of the paradoxes fall foul of the extended liar paradox: &amp;ldquo;this sentence is not true.&amp;rdquo; If we pay attention to the role of assertion and denial and the behaviour of negation in both &amp;ldquo;gap&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;glut&amp;rdquo; analyses, we see that the situation with these approaches has a pleasing symmetry: gap approaches take some denials to not be expressible by negation, and glut approaches take some negations to not express denials. But in the light of this symmetry, considerations against a gap view point to parallel considerations against a glut view. Those who find some reason to prefer one view over another (and this is almost everyone) must find some reason to break this symmetry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This short paper was written for presentation at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.philosophy.unimelb.edu.au/aap2004&#34;&gt;AAP2004&lt;/a&gt;. After very many revisions, it&amp;rsquo;s finally going to be published in an edited collection from members and friends of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/arche/projects/logic/&#34;&gt;Arché project on Foundations of Logical Consequence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Normal Proofs, Cut Free Derivations and Structural Rules</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/npcfdsr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/npcfdsr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Different natural deduction proof systems for intuitionistic and classical logic&amp;mdash;and related logical systems&amp;mdash;differ in fundamental properties while sharing significant family resemblances. These differences become quite stark when it comes to the structural rules of contraction and weakening. In this paper, I show how Gentzen and Jas&amp;#x301;kowski&amp;rsquo;s natural deduction systems differ in fine structure. I also motivate directed proof nets as another natural deduction system which shares some of the design features of Genzen and Jas&amp;#x301;kowski&amp;rsquo;s systems, but which differs again in its treatment of the structural rules, and has a range of virtues absent from traditional natural deduction systems.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Pluralism and Proofs</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/pluralism-and-proofs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/pluralism-and-proofs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Beall and Restall&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Logical Pluralism&lt;/em&gt; (2006) characterises pluralism about logical consequence in terms of the different ways cases can be selected in the analysis of logical consequence as preservation of truth over a class of cases. This is not the only way to understand or to motivate pluralism about logical consequence. Here, I will examine pluralism about logical consequence in terms of different standards of proof. We will focus on sequent derivations for classical logic, imposing two different restrictions on classical derivations to produce derivations focusr intuitionistic logic and for dual intuitionistic logic. The result is another way to understand the manner in which we can have different consequence relations in the same language. Furthermore, the proof-theoretic perspective gives us a different explanation of how the one concept of negation can have three different truth conditions, those in classical, intuitionistic and dual-intuitionistic models.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Assertion, Denial and Non-Classical Theories</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/adnct/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/adnct/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;In this paper I urge friends of truth-value gaps and truth-value gluts &amp;ndash; proponents of paracomplete and paraconsistent logics &amp;ndash; to consider theories not merely as sets of sentences, but as &lt;em&gt;pairs&lt;/em&gt; of sets of sentences, or what I call &amp;lsquo;bitheories,&amp;rsquo; which keep track not only of what &lt;em&gt;holds&lt;/em&gt; according to the theory, but also what &lt;em&gt;fails&lt;/em&gt; to hold according to the theory.  I explain the connection between bitheories, sequents, and the speech acts of assertion and denial. I illustrate the usefulness of bitheories by showing how they make available a technique for characterising different theories while abstracting away from logical vocabulary such as connectives or quantifiers, thereby making theoretical commitments independent of the choice of this or that particular non-classical logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples discussed include theories of numbers, classes and truth.  In the latter two cases, the bitheoretical perspective brings to light some heretofore unconsidered puzzles for friends of na&amp;iuml;ve theories of classes and truth.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Special Issue of the Logic Journal of the IGPL: Non-Classical Mathematics</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/ncm-igpl-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/ncm-igpl-2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;A special issue of the Logic Journal of the IGPL, on Non-Classical Mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editorial Preface&lt;/em&gt;, Libor B&amp;#x115;hounek, Greg Restall, and Giovanni Sambin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Mathematical pluralism,&amp;quot; Graham Priest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;A first constructive look at the comparison of projections,&amp;quot; Douglas S. Bridges and Lumini&amp;#x163;a S. V&amp;icirc;&amp;#x163;a&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Lipschitz functions in constructive reverse mathematics,&amp;quot; Iris Loeb&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Constructive version of Boolean algebra,&amp;quot; Francesco Ciraulo, Maria Emilia Maietti, and Paola Toto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;A generalized cut characterization of the fullness axiom in CZF,&amp;quot; Laura Crosilla, Erik Palmgren, and Peter Schuster&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Interpreting lattice-valued set theory in fuzzy set theory,&amp;quot; Petr H&amp;aacute;jek and Zuzana Hanikov&amp;aacute;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;On equality and natural numbers in Cantor-&amp;#x141;ukasiewicz set theory,&amp;quot; Petr H&amp;aacute;jek&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Identity taken seriously: a non-classical approach,&amp;quot; Chris Mortensen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Strong, universal and provably non-trivial set theory by means of adaptive logic,&amp;quot; Peter Verdee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire issue can be &lt;a href=&#34;http://jigpal.oxfordjournals.org/content/21/1.toc&#34;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>New Waves in Philosophical Logic</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/new-waves-in-philosophical-logic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/new-waves-in-philosophical-logic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Philosophical logic has been, and continues to be, a driving force behind much progress and development in philosophy more broadly. This collection of 12 original papers by 15 up-and-coming philosophical logicians deals with a broad range of topics, including proof-theory, probability, context-sensitivity, dialetheism and dynamic semantics. If the discipline&amp;rsquo;s past influence on the core areas of philosophy is anything to go by, then the scholars and the ideas in these pages are the ones to watch. Here are the essays in the volume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://consequently.org/papers/NewWavesIntroduction.pdf&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;, Greg Restall and Gillian Russell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Things Are Elsewhere, Wolfgang Schwarz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Change and First-Order Dynamic Logic, Barteld Kooi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://consequently.org/writing/interp-apply-ptml&#34;&gt;Interpreting and Applying Proof Theories for Modal Logic&lt;/a&gt;, Francesca Poggiolesi and Greg Restall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Logic(s) of Modal Knowledge, Daniel Cohnitz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From Type-Free Truth to Type-Free Probability, Hannes Leitgeb&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dogmatism, Probability and Logical Uncertainty, David Jehle and Brian Weatherson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skepticism about Reasoning, Sherrilyn Roush, Kelty Allen and Ian Herbert&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lessons in Philosophy of Logic from Medieval Obligationes, Catarina Dutilh Novaes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Rule Out Things with Words:Strong Paraconsistency and the Algebra of Exclusion, Francesco Berto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lessons from the Logic of Demonstratives, Gillian Russell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Multitude View on Logic, Matti Eklund&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>A Cut-Free Sequent System for Two-Dimensional Modal Logic, and why it matters</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/cfss2dml/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/cfss2dml/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;The two-dimensional modal logic of Davies and Humberstone is an important aid to our understanding the relationship between actuality, necessity and a priori knowability. I show how a cut-free hypersequent calculus for 2d modal logic not only captures the logic precisely, but may be used to address issues in the epistemology and metaphysics of our modal concepts. I will explain how use of our concepts motivates the inference rules of the sequent calculus, and then show that the completeness of the calculus for Davies&amp;ndash;Humberstone models explains why those concepts have the structure described by those models. The result is yet another application of the completeness theorem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This paper was awarded a Silver Medal for the Kurt Go&amp;#x308;del Prize in 2011.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Bradwardine Hypersequents</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/bradwardine-hypersequents/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Aug 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/bradwardine-hypersequents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;According to Stephen Read, Thomas Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s theory of truth provides an independently motivated solution to the paradoxes of truth, such as the liar. In a series of papers, I have discussed modal models for Read&amp;rsquo;s reconstruction of Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s theory. In this paper, provide a hypersequent calculus for this theory, and I show that the cut rule is admissible in the hypersequent calculus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This paper is dedicated to Professor Stephen Read, whose work has been a profound influence on my own. His work on relevant logic, on proof theoretical harmony, on the logic of identity and on Thomas Brad- wardine&amp;rsquo;s theory of truth have been a rich source of insight, of stimulation and of provocation. In an attempt to both honour Stephen, and hopefully to give him some pleasure, I am going to attempt to cook up something original using some of the many and varied ingredients he has provided us. In this paper, I will mix and match ideas and techniques from Stephen&amp;rsquo;s papers on proof theory, on Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s theory of truth, and on identity to offer a harmonious sequent system for a theory of truth inspired by Stephen Read&amp;rsquo;s recovery of the work of Thomas Bradwardine.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Interpreting and Applying Proof Theories for Modal Logics</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/interp-apply-ptml/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/interp-apply-ptml/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Proof theory for modal logic has blossomed over recent years. Many ex- tensions of the classical sequent calculus have been proposed in order to give natural and appealing accounts of proof in modal logics like K, T, S4, S5, provability logics, and other modal systems. The common feature of each of these different proof systems consists in the general structure of the rules for modal operators. They provide introduction and elimination rules for statements of the form  &amp;#x25A1;&amp;#x10FC05;A (and &amp;#x25C7;&amp;#x10FC06;A), which show how those statements can feature as conclusions or as premises in deduction. These rules give an account of the deductive power of a modal formula 􏰅&amp;#x25A1;&amp;#x10FC05;A (and 􏰆&amp;#x25C7;&amp;#x10FC06;A) in terms of the constituent formula A.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distinctive feature for the modal operators in contemporary proof systems for modal logics is that the step introducing or eliminating 􏰅􏰅&amp;#x25A1;&amp;#x10FC05;A is at the cost of introducing or eliminating some kind of extra structure in the proof. In this way, the proof rules for modal concepts such as 􏰅􏰅&amp;#x25A1;&amp;#x10FC05; run in parallel with the truth conditions for these concepts in a Kripke model, in which the truth of 􏰅􏰅&amp;#x25A1;&amp;#x10FC05;A stands or falls with the truth of A, but at the cost of checking that truth elsewhere, at points in the model accessible from the point at which 􏰅􏰅&amp;#x25A1;&amp;#x10FC05;A is evaluated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper we will introduce these recent advances in proof theory for a general audience, and then we will show how they are connected  with different—metaphysical and epistemic—conceptions of modality. We will show that these different pictures are nothing but different ways of connecting the statement 􏰅􏰅&amp;#x25A1;&amp;#x10FC05;A with the statement A, of showing the significance of modalising. In the light of this result we will draw conclusions about the link between analyticity and modality, and about the nature of a proof system for modal logics.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>History of Logical Consequence</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/hlc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/hlc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Consequence is &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;, if not &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt;, core subject matter of logic. Aristotle&amp;rsquo;s study of the syllogism instigated the task of categorising arguments into the logically good and the logically bad; the task remains an essential element of the study of logic. In this essay, we give a quick history of the way logical consequence has been studied from Aristotle to the present day.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>On the ternary relation and conditionality</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/ternary-cond/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/ternary-cond/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;One of the most dominant approaches to semantics for relevant (and many paraconsistent) logics is the Routley–Meyer semantics involving a ternary relation on points. To some (many?), this ternary relation has seemed like a technical trick devoid of an intuitively appealing philosophical story that connects it up with conditionality in general. In this paper, we respond to this worry by providing three different philosophical accounts of the ternary relation that correspond to three conceptions of conditionality. We close by briefly discussing a general conception of conditionality that may unify the three given conceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Molinism and the Thin Red Line</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/molinism-trl/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/molinism-trl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Molinism is an attempt to do equal justice to divine foreknowledge and human freedom.  For Molinists, human freedom &lt;em&gt;fits&lt;/em&gt; in this universe for the future is open or unsettled.  However, God&amp;rsquo;s middle knowledge &amp;ndash; God&amp;rsquo;s contingent knowledge of what agents would freely do in this or that circumstance &amp;ndash; underwrites God&amp;rsquo;s omniscience in the midst of this openness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper I rehearse Nuel Belnap and Mitchell Green&amp;rsquo;s argument in &amp;lsquo;Indeterminism and the Thin Red Line&amp;rsquo; against the reality of a distinguished single future in the context of branching time, and show that it applies applies equally against Molinism + branching time.  In the process, we show how contemporary work in the logic of temporal notions in the context of branching time (specifically, Prior&amp;ndash;Thomason semantics) can illuminate discussions in the metaphysics of freedom and divine knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Anti-Realist Classical Logic and Realist Mathematics</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/antirealist/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/antirealist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;I sketch an application of a semantically anti-realist understanding of the classical sequent calculus to the topic of mathematics. The result is a semantically anti-realist defence of mathematical realism. In the paper, I develop the view and compare it to orthodox positions in the philosophy of mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Logic in Australasia</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/logic_in_australasia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/logic_in_australasia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;This is an idiosyncratic history of philosophical logic in Australia and New Zealand, highlighting two significant points of research in Australasian philosophical logic: modal logic and relevant/paraconsistent logic.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>On the ternary relation and conditionality</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/sitconchan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/sitconchan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Majer and Peli&amp;scaron; have proposed a relevant logic for epistemic agents, providing a novel extension of the relevant logic R with a distinctive epistemic modality K, which is at the one and the same time factive (K&amp;phi; &amp;rarr; &amp;phi; is a theorem) and an existential normal modal operator (K(&amp;phi; &amp;or; &amp;psi;) &amp;rarr; (K&amp;phi; &amp;or; K&amp;psi;) is also a theorem). The intended interpretation is that K&amp;phi; holds (relative to a situation &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;) if there is a resource available at &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;, confirming &amp;phi;. In this article we expand the class of models to the broader class of &amp;lsquo;general epistemic frames&amp;rsquo;. With this generalisation we provide a sound and complete axiomatisation for the logic of general relevant epistemic frames. We also show, that each of the modal axioms characterises some natural subclasses of general frames.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Always More</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/alwaysmore/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/alwaysmore/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;A possible world is a point in logical space. It plays a dual role with respect to propositions. (1) A possible world determines the truth value of every proposition. For each world &lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt; and proposition &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, either at &lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is true, or at &lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is not true. (2) Each set of possible worlds determines a proposition. If &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;, a subset of &lt;em&gt;W&lt;/em&gt; is a set of worlds, there is a proposition &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; true at exactly the worlds in &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I construct a logic, extending classical logic with a single unary operator, which has no complete Boolean algebras as models. If the family of propositions we are talking about in (1) and (2) has the kind of structure described in that logic, then (1) and (2) cannot jointly hold.  I then explain what this might mean for theories of propositions and possible worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Truth Tellers in Bradwardine&#39;s Theory of Truth</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/bradwardine-truth-tellers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Oct 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/bradwardine-truth-tellers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Stephen Read&amp;rsquo;s work on Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s theory of truth is some of the most exciting work on truth and insolubilia in recent years. Read brings together modern tools of formal logic and Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s theory of signification to show that medieval distinctions can give great insight into the behaviour of semantic concepts such as truth. In a number of papers, I have developed a model theory for Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s account of truth. This model theory has distinctive features: it serves up models in which every declarative object (any object signifying &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt;) signifies its own truth. This leads to a puzzle: there are good arguments to the effect that if anything is a truth-teller, it is &lt;em&gt;false&lt;/em&gt;. This is a puzzle. What distinguishes &lt;em&gt;paradoxical&lt;/em&gt; truth-tellers from &lt;em&gt;benign&lt;/em&gt; truth tellers? It is my task in this paper to explain this distinction, and to clarify the behaviour of truth-tellers, given Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s account of signification.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Proof Theory and Meaning: the context of deducibility</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/ptm-context/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Oct 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/ptm-context/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;I examine Belnap&amp;rsquo;s two criteria of &lt;em&gt;existence&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;uniqueness&lt;/em&gt; for evaluating putative definitions of logical concepts in inference rules, by determining how they apply in four different examples: conjunction, the universal quantifier, the indefinite choice operator and the necessity in the modal logic S5.  This illustrates the ways that definitions may be evaluated relative to a background theory of consequence, and the ways that different accounts of consequence provide us with different resources for making definitions.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Decorated Linear Order Types and the Theory of Concatenation</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/dlot/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Oct 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/dlot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;We study the interpretation of Grzegorczyk&amp;rsquo;s Theory of Concatenation TC in structures of decorated linear order types satisfying Grzegorczyk&amp;rsquo;s axioms. We show that TC is incomplete for this interpretation. What is more, the first order theory validated by this interpretation interprets arithmetical truth. We also show that every extension of TC has a model that is not isomorphic to a structure of decorated order types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We provide a positive result, to wit, a construction that builds structures of decorated order types from models of a suitable concatenation theory. This construction has the property that if there is a representation of a certain kind, then the construction provides a representation of that kind.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Barriers to Consequence</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/barriers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/barriers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;In this paper we show how the formal counterexamples to Hume&amp;rsquo;s Law (to the effect that you cannot derive a properly moral statement from properly descriptive statements) are of a piece with formal counterexample to other, plausible &amp;ldquo;inferential barrier theses&amp;rdquo;. We use this fact to motivate a uniform treatment of barrier theses which is immune from formal counterexample. We provide a uniform semantic representation of barrier theses which has applications in the case of what we call &amp;ldquo;Russell&amp;rsquo;s Law&amp;rdquo; (you can&amp;rsquo;t derive a universal from particulars) and &amp;ldquo;Hume&amp;rsquo;s Second Law&amp;rdquo; (you can&amp;rsquo;t derive a statement about the future from statements about the past). We then finally apply these results to formal treatments of deontic logic to show how to avoid formal counterexamples to Hume&amp;rsquo;s Law in a plausible and motivated manner.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Relevant Agents</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/relevant_agents/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/relevant_agents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Majer and Peli&amp;scaron; have proposed a relevant logic for epistemic agents, providing a novel extension of the relevant logic R with a distinctive epistemic modality K, which is at the one and the same time factive (K&amp;phi; &amp;rarr; &amp;phi; is a theorem) and an existential normal modal operator (K(&amp;phi; &amp;or; &amp;psi;) &amp;rarr; (K&amp;phi; &amp;or; K&amp;psi;) is also a theorem). The intended interpretation is that K&amp;phi; holds (relative to a situation s) if there is a resource available at s, confirming &amp;phi;. In this article we expand the class of models to the broader class of &amp;lsquo;general epistemic frames&amp;rsquo;. With this generalisation we provide a sound and complete axiomatisation for the logic of general relevant epistemic frames. We also show, that each of the modal axioms characterises some natural subclasses of general frames.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>On t and u, and what they can do</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/on_t_and_u/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/on_t_and_u/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;This paper shows that once we have propositional constants &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; (the conjunction of all truths) and &lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt; (the disjunction of all untruths), paradox ensues, provided you have a conditional in the language strong enough to give you &lt;em&gt;modus ponens&lt;/em&gt;.  This is an issue for views like those of Jc Beall, Ross Brady, Hartry Field and Graham Priest.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>What are we to accept, and what are we to reject, when saving truth from paradox?</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/stp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/stp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;In this article, I praise Hartry Field&amp;rsquo;s fine book &lt;em&gt;Saving Truth From Paradox&lt;/em&gt; (Oxford University Press, 2008).  I also show that his account of properties is threatened by a paradox,  and I explain how we can only avoid this paradox by coming to a clearer understanding the connections between accepting and rejecting (or assertion and denial) and the identity conditions for properties.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Models for Substructural Arithmetics</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/mfsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2009 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/mfsa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;This paper explores models for arithmetics in substructural logics.  In the existing literature on substructural arithmetic, frame semantics for substructural logics are absent.  We will start to fill in the picture in this paper by examining frame semantics for the substructural logics C (linear logic plus distribution), R (relevant logic) and CK (C plus weakening).  The eventual goal is to find negation complete models for arithmetic in R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper is dedicated to Professor Robert K. Meyer.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>On Permutation in Simplified Semantics</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/permutation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2009 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/permutation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;This note explains an error in Restall&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Simplified Semantics for Relevant Logics (and some of their rivals)&amp;rsquo; (&lt;em&gt;Journal of Philosophical Logic&lt;/em&gt; 1993) concerning the modelling conditions for the axioms of &lt;em&gt;assertion&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; &amp;rarr; ((&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; &amp;rarr; &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt;) &amp;rarr; &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt;)  and &lt;em&gt;permutation&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; &amp;rarr; (&lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt; &amp;rarr; &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt;)) &amp;rarr; (&lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt; &amp;rarr; (&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; &amp;rarr; &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt;)).  We show that the modelling conditions for assertion and permutation proposed in &amp;lsquo;Simplified Semantics&amp;rsquo; overgenerate. In fact, they overgenerate so badly that the proposed semantics for the relevant logic R validate the rule of disjunctive syllogism.  The semantics provides for &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; models of R in which the &amp;ldquo;base point&amp;rdquo; is inconsistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this note, we explain this result, diagnose the mistake in &amp;lsquo;Simplified Semantics&amp;rsquo; and propose a correction.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>A Priori Truths</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/apriori/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2009 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/apriori/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Philosophers love a priori knowledge: we delight in truths that can be known from the comfort of our armchairs, without the need to venture out in the world for cofirmation.  This is due not to laziness, but to two different considerations.  First, it seems that many philosophical issues aren&amp;rsquo;t settled by our experience of the world &amp;ndash; the nature of morality; the way concepts pick out objects; the structure of our experience of the world in which we find ourselves &amp;ndash; these issues seem to be decided not on the basis of our experience, but in some manner by things prior to (or independently of) that experience.  Second, even when we are deeply interested in how our experience lends credence to our claims about the world, the matter remains of the remainder: we learn more about how experience contributes to knowledge when we see what knowledge is available independent of that experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this essay we will look at the topic of what can be known &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Truth Values and Proof Theory</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/tvpt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2009 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/tvpt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;In this paper I present an account of truth values for &lt;em&gt;classical logic&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;intuitionistic logic&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;the modal logic S5&lt;/em&gt;, in which truth values are not a fundamental category from which the logic is defined, but rather, feature as an idealisation of more fundamental logical features arising out of the proof theory for each system. The result is not a new set of semantic structures, but a new understanding of how the existing semantic structures may be understood in terms of a more fundamental notion of logical consequence.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Using Peer Instruction to Teach Philosophy, Logic and Critical Thinking</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/peer-instruction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2009 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/peer-instruction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;We explain how &lt;a href=&#34;http://mazur-www.harvard.edu/emdetails.php&#34;&gt;Eric Mazur&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s technique of Peer Instruction may be used to teach philosophy, logic and critical thinking &amp;mdash; to good effect.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Appendix to &#39;Yo!&#39; and &#39;Lo!&#39;: the pragmatic topography of the space of reasons</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/yo-lo-appendix/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/yo-lo-appendix/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;The appendix to Kukla and Lance&amp;rsquo;s book is the preliminary development of a score-keeping semantics that begins with the broader field of vision opened up when we eschew the declarative fallacy and make use of abstract versions of the pragmatic distinctions developed in the body of the book.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Models for Liars in Bradwardine&#39;s Theory of Truth</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/bradwardine-liars/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/bradwardine-liars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Stephen Read&amp;rsquo;s work on Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s theory of truth is some of the most exciting work on truth and insolubilia in recent years. In this paper, I give models for Read&amp;rsquo;s formulation of Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s theory of truth, and I examine the behaviour of liar sentences in those models. I conclude by examining Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s argument to the effect that if something signifies itself to be untrue then it signifies itself to be true as well. We will see that there are models in which this conclusion fails. This should help us elucidate the hidden assumptions required to underpin Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s argument, and to make explicit the content of Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s theory of truth.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Truthmakers, Entailment and Necessity 2008</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/ten2008/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/ten2008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;
I update &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://consequently.org/writing/ten/&#34;&gt;Truthmakers, Entailment and Necessity&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; with a response to Stephen Read&#39;s wonderful &lt;em&gt;Mind&lt;/em&gt; 2000 argument to the effect that I got the disjunction thesis wrong.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think I didn&#39;t get it wrong, but figuring out &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it&#39;s OK to hold that a truthmaker makes a disjunction true iff it makes a disjunct true is not as straightforward as I first thought.  Pluralism about truthmaking makes an entrance.
&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Proof Theory and Philosophy</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/ptp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/ptp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;This is my next book-length writing project.  I am writing a book which aims to do these things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li /&gt; Be a useable textbook in philosophical logic, accessible to someone who&amp;rsquo;s done only an intro course in logic, covering at least some model theory and proof theory of propositional logic, and maybe predicate logic.
&lt;li /&gt; Be a user-friendly, pedagogically useful and philosophically motivated presentation of cut-elimination, normalisation and conservative extension, both (a) why they&amp;rsquo;re important to meaning theory and (b) how to actually &lt;em&gt;prove&lt;/em&gt; them.  (I don&amp;rsquo;t think there are any books like this available, but I&amp;rsquo;d be happy to be shown wrong.)
&lt;li /&gt; Present the duality between model theory and proof theory in a philosophically illuminating fashion.
&lt;li /&gt; Teach both formal philosophical logic in such a way that is not doctrinaire or logically partisan.  That is, I will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; argue that classical logic, or that intuitionistic logic, or that My Favourite Logic is the One True Logic. (Of course, hearing me say this is &lt;a href=&#34;http://consequently.org/writing/logical_pluralism/&#34;&gt;not a surprise&lt;/a&gt;.)
&lt;li /&gt; I am (at this stage, at least) planning to make the book &lt;a href=&#34;http://consequently.org/news/2004/03/18/publishing_a_book&#34;&gt;available for download&lt;/a&gt; as well as published by an academic publisher.
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first couple of chapters are now available: &lt;a href=&#34;http://consequently.org/papers/ptp.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf with hyperlinks&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://consequently.org/papers/ptp-2up.pdf&#34;&gt;paper-saving 2up pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Modal Models for Bradwardine&#39;s Theory of Truth</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/bradwardine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/bradwardine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Stephen Read has recently discussed Thomas Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s theory of truth, and defended it as an appropriate way to treat paradoxes such as the liar. In this paper, I discuss Read&amp;rsquo;s formalisation of Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s theory of truth, and provide a class of models for this theory.  The models facilitate comparison of Bradwardine&amp;rsquo;s theory with contemporary theories of truth.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Envelopes and Indifference</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/envelopes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/envelopes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;We diagnose the two envelope &amp;ldquo;paradox&amp;rdquo;, showing how the indifference principle plays a role in prompting the conflicting assignments of the expected outcomes for switching or keeping.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Curry&#39;s Revenge: the costs of non-classical solutions to the paradoxes of self-reference</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/costing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/costing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;I point out that non-classical &amp;ldquo;solutions&amp;rdquo; the paradoxes of self-reference are non-particularly easy to give. Curry&amp;rsquo;s paradox is very very hard to avoid, if you wish to give a semantically cohrerent picture.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Assertion and Denial, Commitment and Entitlement, and Incompatibility (and some consequence)</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/acdei/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/acdei/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;In this short paper, I compare and contrast the kind of symmetricalist treatment of negation favoured in different ways by Huw Price (in &amp;ldquo;Why &amp;lsquo;Not&amp;rsquo;?&amp;rdquo;) and by me (in &amp;ldquo;Multiple Conclusions&amp;rdquo;) with Robert Brandom&amp;rsquo;s analysis of scorekeeping in terms of commitment, entitlement and incompatibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both kinds of account provide a way to distinguish the inferential significance of &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; is warranted&amp;rdquo; in terms of a subtler analysis of our practices: on the one hand, we assert as well as deny; on the other, by distingushing downstream commitments from upstream entitlements and the incompatibility definable in terms of these.  In this note I will examine the connections between these different approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>A Participatory Theory of the Atonement</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/pa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/pa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;We argue that the participatory language, used in the New Testament to describe the the efficacy of Jesus&amp;rsquo; death on the cross, is essential for any understanding of the atonement. Purely personal or legal metaphors are incomplete and perhaps misleading on their own. They make much more sense when combined with and undergirded by, participatory metaphors.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Review of Ross Brady, Universal Logic</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/universal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2007 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/universal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;This solid volume with the ominous black cover and eerie glowing disc lettered with inscrutable strings of characters such as &amp;ldquo;DN&lt;sup&gt;d&lt;/sup&gt;Q,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;LSDJ&lt;sup&gt;d&lt;/sup&gt;,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;L2LDJQ&lt;sup&gt;&amp;plusmn;&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;rdquo; is the fruit of over 30 years of Ross Brady&amp;rsquo;s logical labours. And it is worth the wait&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Invention is the Mother of Necessity: modal logic, modal semantics and modal metaphysics</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/invention/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2007 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/invention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Modal logic is a well-established field, and the possible worlds semantics of modal logics has proved invaluable to our understanding of the logical features of the modal concepts such as possibility and necessity. However, the significance of possible worlds models for a genuine theory of meaning&amp;ndash;let alone for metaphysics&amp;ndash;is less clear. In this paper I shall explain how and why the use of the concepts of necessity and possibility could arise (and why they have the logical behaviour charted out by standard modal logics) without either taking the notions of necessity or possibility as primitive, and without starting with possible worlds. Once we give an account of modal logic we can then go on to give an account of possible worlds, and explain why possible worlds semantics is a natural fit for modal logic without being the source of modal concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper is an early draft, and comments are most welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Symbolic Logic</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/symbolic-logic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2007 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/symbolic-logic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;1007 words on symbolic logic &amp;ndash; concentrating on the history of 20th Century logic, aimed at an audience of social scientists&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Proofnets for S5&amp;#58; sequents and circuits for modal logic</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/s5nets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2007 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/s5nets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;In this paper I introduce a sequent system for the propositional modal logic S5.  Derivations of valid sequents in the system are shown to correspond to proofs in a novel natural deduction system of &lt;em&gt;circuit proofs&lt;/em&gt; (reminiscient of proofnets in linear logic, or multiple-conclusion calculi for classical logic).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sequent derivations and proofnets are both simple extensions of sequents and proofnets for classical propositional logic, in which the new machinery&amp;mdash;to take account of the modal vocabulary&amp;mdash;is directly motivated in terms of the simple, universal Kripke semantics for S5.
The sequent system is cut-free and the circuit proofs are normalising.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Proof Theory and Meaning: on second order logic</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/ptm-second-order/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2007 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/ptm-second-order/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Second order quantification is puzzling. The second order quantifiers have natural and compelling inference rules, and they also have natural models. These do not match: the inference rules are sound for the models, but not complete, so either the proof rules are too weak or the models are too strong. Some, such as Quine, take this to be no real problem, since they take &amp;ldquo;second order logic&amp;rdquo; to be a misnomer. It is not logic but set theory in sheep&amp;rsquo;s clothing, so one would not expect to have a sound and complete axiomatisation of the theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that this judgement is incorrect, and in this paper I attempt to explain why. I show how on Nuel Belnap&amp;rsquo;s criterion for logicality, second order quantification can count as properly logic so-called, since the quantifiers are properly defined by their inference rules, and the addition of second order quantification to a basic language is conservative. With this notion of logicality in hand I then diagnose the incompleteness of the proof theory of second order logic in what seems to be a novel way.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
 
    <item>
      <title>Logics, Situations and Channels</title>
      <link>http://consequently.org/writing/channels/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2006 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://consequently.org/writing/channels/</guid>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;The notion of that information is relative to a context is important in many different ways. The idea that the context is &lt;em&gt;small&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; that is, not necessarily a consistent and complete possible world &amp;ndash; plays a role not only in situation theory, but it is also an enlightening perspective from which to view other areas, such as modal logics, relevant logics, categorial grammar and much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article we will consider these areas, and focus then on one further question: How can we account for information about one thing giving us information about something else? This is a question addressed by channel theory. We will look at channel theory and then see how the issues of information flow and conditionality play a role in each of the different domains we have examined.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>